<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
 * 
 * This help file was generated from arfit.sci using help_from_sci().
 * 
 -->

<refentry version="5.0-subset Scilab" xml:id="arfit" xml:lang="en"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">


  <refnamediv>
    <refname>arfit</refname><refpurpose>Stepwise least squares estimation of multivariate AR model.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>



<refsynopsisdiv>
   <title>Calling Sequence</title>
   <synopsis>
   [w, A, C, sbc, fpe, th]=arfit(v, pmin, pmax)
   [w, A, C, sbc, fpe, th]=arfit(v, pmin, pmax, SELECTOR)
   [w, A, C, sbc, fpe, th]=arfit(v, pmin, pmax, SELECTOR, no_const)
   [w, A, C, sbc, fpe, th]=arfit(v, pmin, pmax, SELECTOR, no_const, min_order)
   </synopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection>
   <title>Description</title>
   <para>
[w,A,C,SBC,FPE,th]=arfit(v,pmin,pmax) produces estimates of the
parameters of a multivariate AR model of order p,
   </para>
   <para>
v(k,:)' = w' + A1*v(k-1,:)' +...+ Ap*v(k-p,:)' + noise(C),
   </para>
   <para>
where p lies between pmin and pmax and is chosen as the optimizer
of Schwarz's Bayesian Criterion. The input matrix v must contain
the time series data, with columns (first dimension) of v(:,l)
representing variables l=1,...,m and rows v(k,:) (second
dimension) of v representing observations at different (equally
spaced) times k=1,..,n. Optionally, v can have a third
dimension, in which case the matrices v(:,:, itr) represent
the realizations (e.g., measurement trials) itr=1,...,ntr of the
time series. ARFIT returns least squares estimates of the
intercept vector w, of the coefficient matrices A1,...,Ap (as
A=[A1 ... Ap]), and of the noise covariance matrix C.
   </para>
   <para>
   </para>
   <para>
As order selection criteria, arfit computes approximations to
Schwarz's Bayesian Criterion and to the logarithm of Akaike's Final
Prediction Error. The order selection criteria for models of order
pmin:pmax are returned as the vectors SBC and FPE.
   </para>
   <para>
The matrix th contains information needed for the computation of
confidence intervals. armode and arconf require th as input
arguments.
   </para>
   <para>
If the optional argument SELECTOR is included in the function call,
as in arfit(v,pmin,pmax,SELECTOR), SELECTOR is used as the order
selection criterion in determining the optimum model order. The
three letter string SELECTOR must have one of the two values 'sbc'
or 'fpe'. (By default, Schwarz's criterion SBC is used.) If the
bounds pmin and pmax coincide, the order of the estimated model
is p=pmin=pmax.
   </para>
   <para>
If the function call contains the optional argument 'zero' as the
fourth or fifth argument, a model of the form
   </para>
   <para>
v(k,:)' = A1*v(k-1,:)' +...+ Ap*v(k-p,:)' + noise(C)
   </para>
   <para>
is fitted to the time series data. That is, the intercept vector w
is taken to be zero, which amounts to assuming that the AR(p)
process has zero mean.
   </para>
   <para>
Modified 19.09.2007 by German Gomez-Herrero, german.gomezherrero@ieee.org
- New input flag min_order tells the function to try to minimize the
selected model order by taking that order from which the selection
criteria decreases very slowly
   </para>
   <para>
Modified 11-06-2007 by German Gomez-Herrero, german.gomezherrero@ieee.org
- Added AIC criterion
- First input parameter can be a ddataset object (to save memory resources)
   </para>
   <para>
</para>
</refsection>

<refsection>
   <title>Authors</title>
   <simplelist type="vert">
   <member>Modified 14-Oct-00</member>
   <member>24-Oct-10 Tim Mullen (added support for multiple realizatons)</member>
   <member>Tapio Schneider   tapio@gps.caltech.edu</member>
   <member>Arnold Neumaier  neum@cma.univie.ac.a</member>
   </simplelist>
</refsection>
</refentry>
